I hope you had some fun playing around with some of the code blocks.
So let's continue our learning journey and see what else we can do.
But before we move on and build some awesome games and apps and animations, we first need to talk about
what all these groups of code blocks are and what their purpose is.
Because if we can properly understand what each group does from the start, you will find it much easier
to create your own code.
As we've seen, all the blocks in scratch are organized into different groups.
As you can see, all these are blue, these are purple, these are pink, and so on.
Basically, each of these are grouped by what they do and they represent different aspects of programming.
So let's go through each of the groups to understand their purpose, and also see some of the fun things
that they can do.
Virtually all these blue blocks are to do with motion and moving your sprite around the screen, and
we've been playing quite a bit with this group of code, so I'm sure you have a pretty good idea of
what it's all about.
But there is a bunch more you can do here using motion blocks.
But moving on.
Yeah, there's going to be funny.
Uh, the next group is looks, and this is all about.
Yeah, well, you guessed it looks.
So.
Let's have a look.
We have also tried out some of the code blocks, like switching the costumes, saying different words,
or even changing the color, but there's still a lot more we can do, like change the size and make
the cat bigger, or make it hide or show and lots more.
But basically all you need to know is that the looks group is all to do with looks, and we will often
use this when we want to create fancy graphics and animations, which you will see later on.
Moving down.
We have sounds, and I'm sure you can guess what this is about.
Here we can have our sprites make specific sounds.
So with our cat, we can have it make this meow sound.
And we can also change the pitch, as you can see.
And yes, it does start to get a bit crazy.
Okay.
Moving down, our next group is called events, and you might not be too sure what this group is about.
However, this is very important group of code blocks because it allows us to automatically play our
scripts when a certain event happens.
So far we have used the when flag clicked event, which basically starts our code scripts when this
green flag is clicked, and you'll see how useful this is when we have lots of sprites.
But as you can see, there are other events like when space clicked.
This will only start the script when the spacebar is clicked, or this event starts, the script when
the sprite is clicked, or when I receive a message.
These events all do the same thing.
Instead of waiting for us to click the green flag to play our code, they will wait for something else
to happen.
And this allows us to control when code should start.
Now you will really get to know how this all works when we make some more advanced applications later,
but with that, we can move to our next group of code, which is control.
All the blocks in here are used to control our code, which basically means they help us manage the
flow and structure of our scripts.
Kind of like how traffic lights help direct cars at busy intersections.
For example, we have blocks for creating loops, which let us repeat sections of code a specific number
of times or even forever.
Just like we did earlier to get our cat to walk to the end of the screen or constantly follow our mouse
pointer.
We also have conditional statements like if, then and if, then else blocks which allow sprites to
make decisions based on certain conditions being met, similar to how you might choose to wear a coat
if it's raining or wear sunglasses if it's sunny outside.
There's also this block here which weights.
Moving this into our script, you will notice how now when I click the flag, it waits for one second
before it plays the script.
This is also an important thing to note, so pay close attention.
When we run one of our scripts, like this one.
For example, the code runs in a top down order, so we can look at it logically.
When we click the flag, it will first wait for one second, and this is the first block of code.
Then it will change color by 25 and then point towards the mouse pointer.
And of course this will forever loop this code here.
But if you play the script, it does seem like it is.
Both these code blocks are running at the same time, and this is because computers are so fast that
you can't even notice this is happening in order.
But let's add some white blocks to see it in action.
So dragging in our wait one second here and another here before I run the code, can you guess what
it's going to do?
Think?
Guess.
What will the weights do?
We click the flag, it waits for one second.
It changes color, waits for another second, points towards the mouse, waits for another second.
Then it goes back to changing the color and so on.
So playing this program, you can see how it does exactly what we predicted and how it happens in the
order we specified.
And as we move on, you'll see how the order in which we place our code is so important.
But on that topic, these control blocks give us the power to make our project smarter and more interactive
by responding to different situations as they happen.
And there's still a bunch more, but you will get the idea.
For now.
Moving down to the next group, we have sensing and these blocks are pretty cool.
Sensing blocks let your sprites detect things like touching another sprite, a mouse movement, or even
listening for what a user types.
These blocks help your projects react to their environment, and this is very handy when we want to
build interactive games and we'll play with some of these later on when we make some fun games.
Moving down again.
We have operators and this is all to do with math.
And yeah, yeah, math can be boring sometimes, but I will tell you that when we are making games,
we need some math to make it work and it becomes a whole lot of fun.
Operators are kind of like the tools we use to build and solve puzzles in our project.
They help us do math and make comparisons, just like we do when we are figuring things out in everyday
life.
For example, we can add, subtract, multiply, or divide numbers together.
Find the remainder when one number is divided by another, or even pick a random number.
These operators.
Also, let us compare values to see if they're equal greater than or less than one another.
It's like when you're playing a card game and you need to figure out who has the highest card.
We use comparisons to decide who wins and not just numbers.
We can even combine text, also known as strings, to create sentences or make our sprites say pretty
funny things.
So operators give us a whole bunch of cool tools to work with when we're creating our games and projects
in scratch, and they'll help us make our projects more dynamic and interactive.
And finally we have variables.
Variables are like little storage boxes for information that we can use in our projects.
Imagine you're playing a game and and you have a score.
Where would you keep track of that score?
You got it in a variable.
In scratch.
We can create our very own variables to store and keep track of different values like scores, lives,
or even a player's name.
We can change these values by adding, subtracting, setting, or even showing and hiding the variable
on the screen.
Just like in the real world, we use notes to remember important information that we might need later
on.
In scratch and programming, we use variables.
For example, let's say you're making a game where a character collects coins each time they collect
a coin.
You'd want to increase this score by one.
You could use a variable to store the player's score, and then add one to it every time they pick up
a coin.
Variables are super helpful in making our games and projects more engaging, interactive, and fun.
Plus, they help us keep track of important information as our projects get more complex.
Looking down again, you will see there is one more area called my blocks and as you can see, there
is nothing here at the moment.
But we will look at using the special code block in more advanced lessons.
Anyway, that's about it.
In this lesson, you really gained a good basic understanding of how all these blocks work together
to form complex scripts that can help us make awesome games.
We also looked at how our code goes in order from top to bottom, and also always test some of the blocks.
Now for yourself and see if you can get something fun going on by creating some of your own cool scripts.
And I'll see you in the next lesson as we continue our learning journey.